毛巾
Towels.
米拉兹阁下?
Lord Miraz?
您有儿子了
You have a son.
上天保佑
The heavens have blessed us.
知道怎么做了吧
You know your orders.
葛洛塞将军?
General Glozelle?
遵命 阁下
Yes, my lord.
再睡五分钟
Five more minutes.
今晚不去看星星了 王子
Won't be watching the stars tonight, my prince.
来 我们得快点
Come. We must hurry.
- 老师 发生了什么事? - 你的婶婶刚生了…
- Professor, what's going on? - Your aunt has given birth...
…一个儿子
...to a son.
快来
Come.
你得逃到森林里去
You must make for the woods.
- 森林? - 他们不会追到那的
- The woods? - They won't follow you there.
我花了很多年才找到这个
It has taken me many years to find this.
不到紧急时刻千万不要用
Do not use it except at your greatest need.
我们还会见面吗?
Will I ever see you again?
我希望有那么一天 王子
I dearly hope so, my prince.
我有很多事要告诉你
There is so much more I meant to tell you.
你所知道的一切将会改变
Everything you know is about to change.
拉起吊桥！
Close the drawbridge!
现在 快走
Now, go.
- 站住！ - 站住！
- Halt! - Halt!
一个儿子！一个儿子！
A son! A son!
普鲁娜瑞丝米亚夫人今晚 为米拉兹阁下生了个儿子！
Lady Prunaprismia has this night given Lord Miraz a son!
《纳尼亚传奇2: 凯斯宾王子》
你们这群老迷信 今晚想在牢里过吗?
Which of you superstitious old women wants to spend the night in a cell?
他看见我们了
He's seen us.
看着他
Take care of him.
不！
No!
- 小心点 宝贝 - 抱歉
- Mind yourself, love. - I'm sorry.
看着点路！
Watch where you're going!
等等我！
Wait for me!
你要去圣芬巴?
You go to Saint Finbar's?
没错
That's right.
我要去亨顿屋 就在马路对面
I go to Hendon House. Across the road.
我总见你…
I've seen you...
…一个人坐着
...sitting by yourself.
是啊 我喜欢一个人
Yes, well, I prefer to be left alone.
我也是
Me, too.
你叫什么?
What's your name?
- 菲利斯 - 苏珊！
- Phyllis. - Susan!
你最好快点
You'd better come quickly.
卖报！
Paper here!
今天的报纸！
Get your daily paper!
埃德蒙！
Edmund!
快！打他脸！
Go on! Kick him in the face!
住手 别打了 够了 别打了
Stop it. Break it up. That's enough. Come on.
够了 起来
That's it. Get up.
都几岁了！
Act your age!
- 不用谢 - 我应付得来
- You're welcome. - I had it sorted.
这次又怎么了?
What was it this time?
- 他撞了我 - 就为这你要打他?
- He bumped me. - So you hit him?
不是的 他撞了我 却要我道歉
No. After he bumped me, they tried to make me apologize.
- 所以我才打他的 - 真的?
- That's when I hit him. - Really?
- 退让就那么难吗? - 又不是我的错
- Is it that hard just to walk away? - I shouldn't have to.
我说 老是被当成小孩子 你们就不觉得烦吗?
I mean, don't you ever get tired of being treated like a kid?
我们就是孩子
We are kids.
我不是了
Well, I wasn't always.
已经一年了
It's been a year.
他还要我们等多久?
How long does he expect us to wait?
我们该认清现实了 我们就生活在这
I think it's time to accept that we live here.
假装不同也没用
It's no use pretending any different.
哦 不
Oh, no.
- 假装跟我说话 - 我们本来就在跟你说话
- Pretend you're talking to me. - We are talking to you.
- 安静 露 - 有东西掐我！
- Quiet, Lu. - Something pinched me!
- 别拽了！ - 我没碰你
- Stop pulling! - Not touching you.
听着 你们刚刚…那是什么?
Look, would all of you just... What is that?
- 就像魔法一样 - 大家拉起手
- It feels like magic. - Everyone hold hands.
- 我才不要拉你的手！ - 快…
- I'm not holding your hand! - Just...
你没我快 真羞 埃德！
Shame you're not as quick as me, Ed!
最慢的人是臭蛋
Last one in's a rotten egg.
当心！
Watch out!
来了！
Here it comes!
等等！
Wait a minute!
来 苏珊 快点！
Come on, Susan. Hurry up!
来啊 好漂亮
Come on, it's lovely.
埃德蒙
Edmund.
埃德?埃德！
Ed? Ed!
- 这是什么? - 我们在哪?
- What is it? - Where do you suppose we are?
你觉得呢?
Well, where do you think?
我不记得纳尼亚有废墟
Well, I don't remember any ruins in Narnia.
会是谁住在这呢
Wonder who lived here.
我想是我们
I think we did.
嘿 那是我的
Hey, that's mine.
- 我的国际象棋 - 什么国际象棋?
- From my chess set. - Which chess set?
我在芬奇利可没有纯金象棋 不是吗?
I didn't exactly have a solid gold chess set in Finchley, did I?
不可能
Can't be.
- 没发觉吗? - 什么?
- Don't you see? - What?
想像一下 墙壁
Lmagine walls.
柱子 就在那
And columns, there.
还有玻璃屋顶
And a glass roof.
卡尔帕斯维尔城堡
Cair Paravel.
等等 等一下 阁下 并不是你想的那样
Wait. Wait, my lord. It is not what you think.
那么是怎样呢?
Then what is it?
我们不确定
We're not exactly sure.
不可能
Impossible.
我警告过元老会 信任米拉兹阁下…
I warned this council when it put its trust in Lord Miraz...
- 会有严重后果 - 不
- there would be consequences. - No.
没有证据 我们不能指控护国公
We can't accuse the Lord Protector without proof.
还要用那个借口多久?
How long are we going to hide behind that excuse?
直到这里的席位都空了?
Until every chair in this chamber is empty?
各位元老 抱歉我来晚了
Lords of the council, my apologies for being late.
我不知道要开会
I wasn't aware we were in session.
毫无疑问你有其他事忙
No doubt you were otherwise occupied.
阁下?
My lord?
自凯斯宾九世陛下去世后
Ever since the death of Caspian the ninth,
你就以国王自居
you've behaved as if you were king.
现在在他保护的城堡里 连凯斯宾王子都失踪了
Now it seems that from behind his walls even Prince Caspian has gone missing.
致上我最深的同情 米拉兹阁下
My deepest condolences, Lord Miraz.
想想 你的侄子
Imagine, losing your nephew,
王位的合法继承人
the rightful heir to the throne,
在你夫人诞下一子的晚上失踪了
on the very night your wife has blessed you with a son.
谢谢 索普匹安大人
Thank you, Lord Sopespian.
你的同情在这种困难时刻 确实是最大的恩赐
Your compassion is a boon in this troubled time.
我相信你能告诉我们 悲剧是如何发生的
I trust you can tell us how such a tragedy could have occurred.
真是太令人气愤了
That is the most disturbing news of all.
我们敬爱的凯斯宾…
Our beloved Caspian was abducted...
…被纳尼亚人绑架了
...by Narnians.
你太扯了 米拉兹
You go too far, Miraz.
把这种恶行都推到神话故事上 指望我们会相信你吗?
Expect us to stand by while you blame such a blatant crime on fairy tales?
什么?
What?
我们都忘了 大人们 纳尼亚曾是一片野蛮之地
We forget, my lords, Narnia was once a savage land.
凶猛的生物四处游荡
Fierce creatures roamed free.
为了消灭这些害畜
Much of our forefathers' blood was shed
我们的祖先流了多少血
to exterminate this vermin.
或者我们是这么想的
Or so we thought.
但当我们在争论不休时…
But while we've been bickering amongst ourselves...
…他们却如石下蟑螂一样迅速繁殖
...they've been breeding like cockroaches under a rock!
壮大起来 时刻注视着我们
Growing stronger. Watching us.
等待进攻的时机！
Waiting to strike!
想知道我们为什么不喜欢你嘛
And you wonder why we don't like you.
总之 我打算回击
Well, I intend to strike back.
即使我必须砍倒整片森林
Even if I have to cut down the entire forest,
不过我向你们保证 我会找到凯斯宾王子
I assure you, I will find Prince Caspian
并完成我们祖先的遗愿
and finish what our ancestors began.
- 抛石器 - 什么?
- Catapults. - What?
这发生很久了 卡尔帕斯维尔城堡受到了攻击
This didn't just happen. Cair Paravel was attacked.
你带了火柴吗?
Don't suppose you have any matches, do you?
没有 不过…
No, but...
……这个可以吗?
...would this help?
你应该早点说
You might have mentioned that a bit sooner.
难以置信 所有东西还在这
I can't believe it. It's all still here.
我以前那么高
I was so tall.
你那时更老
Well, you were older then.
几百年后一切却倒过来了…你更年轻了
As opposed to hundreds of years later... when you're younger.
- 这是什么? - 我的号角
- What is it? - My horn.
肯定是回去的那天留在了马鞍上
I must've left it on my saddle the day we went back.
阿斯兰露出牙齿 冬天就过去了
When Aslan bares his teeth, winter meets its death.
他抖抖鬃毛…
When he shakes his mane...
…春天就又回来了
...we shall have spring again.
我们认识的人…杜纳先生和海狸一家…
Everyone we knew... Mr. Tumnus and the Beavers...
…都不在了
...they're all gone.
我们该去搞清楚发生了什么事
I think it's time we found out what's going on.
他一直盯着我们
He won't stop staring.
那就别看了
So don't look.
这够远了
Here's far enough.
放开他！
Drop him!
乌鸦与陶器！
Crows and crockery!
“放开他”！
"Drop him"!
你只会说这个?
That's the best you can come up with?
只需一句简单的“谢谢”就可以了
A simple "thank you" would suffice.
没有你们的帮忙 他们也能把我淹死
They were doing fine drowning me without your help.
也许我们该让他们那么做
Maybe we should have let them.
那他们为什么要杀你呢?
Why were they trying to kill you, anyway?
他们是台尔玛人 专干这种事
They're Telmarines. That's what they do.
台尔玛人?在纳尼亚?
Telmarines? In Narnia?
过去几百年你们去哪了?
Where have you been for the last few hundred years?
说来话长
It's a bit of a long story.
哦 在开玩笑吧
Oh, you've got to be kidding me.
是你们?
You're it?
你们是过去的国王和女王?
You're the kings and queens of old?
至高王彼得 最伟大的
High King Peter, the Magnificent.
你可以不用说后面那词
You probably could've left off the last bit.
也许吧
Probably.
或许你很惊讶
You might be surprised.
你不会想这么做的 孩子
You don't want to do that, boy.
不是我 是他
Not me. Him.
埃德蒙！
Edmund!
没事吧?
You all right?
胡须与床架！
Beards and bedsteads!
也许那个号角最后还是起作用了
Maybe that horn worked after all.
什么号角?
What horn?
这面包不新鲜
This bread is so stale.
我给他弄点汤 他很快会醒过来
I'll just get him some soup. He should be coming around soon.
我觉得我下手不重啊
I don't think I hit him hard enough.
尼卡布瑞克 他还是个孩子
Nikabrik, he's just a boy.
他是台尔玛人 不是迷路的小狗 你说过你会干掉他
He's a Telmarine, not some lost puppy. You said you were gonna get rid of him.
不 我说我会照顾他
No. I said I'd take care of him.
我们现在不能杀他 我才包扎了他的头
We can't kill him now. I just bandaged his head.
现在杀了他就像谋杀一个客人
It would be like murdering a guest.
你觉得他的朋友又会怎么对待他们的客人?
How do you think his friends are treating their guest?
川卜金知道他做了什么 不是这孩子的错
Trumpkin knew what he was doing. It's not the boy's fault.
停下！停下！
Stop! Stop!
住手 不 不！
Hold it. No, no!
跟你说了 那时我们就应该先下手
I told you we should have killed him when we had the chance.
- 你知道我们不能 - 如果我们投票表决 我同意他说的
- You know why we can't. - If we're taking a vote, I'm with him.
我们不能放他走 他看到我们了
We can't let him go. He's seen us.
够了 尼卡布瑞克！
That's enough, Nikabrik!
要我再坐到你头上吗?
Or do I have to sit on your head again?
还有你 看看你都让我做了什么
And you. Look what you made me do.
我花了半个早上熬那个汤
I spent half the morning on that soup.
你是什么?
What are you?
知道吗 你这么问很好笑
You know, it's funny that you would ask that.
你以为人们看到一只獾 就知道是什么了吗
You think people would know a badger when they saw one.
不 不 我是说…
No. No, I mean...
…你们是纳尼亚人 你们应该灭绝了
...you're Narnians. You're supposed to be extinct.
很抱歉让你失望了
Sorry to disappoint you.
给你 还是热的
Here you go. Still hot.
什么时候开始 我们让台尔玛士兵寄宿在这了?
Since when did we open a boarding house for Telmarine soldiers?
我不是士兵
I'm not a soldier.
我是凯斯宾王子 第十任
I am Prince Caspian. The tenth.
你在这干嘛?
What are you doing here?
逃跑
Running away.
我叔叔一直想要我的王位
My uncle has always wanted my throne.
我能活到现在
I suppose I have only lived this long
是因为他没有自己的继承人
because he did not have an heir of his own.
- 情况改变了 - 是啊
- Well, that changes things. - Yeah.
这意味着我们不必亲手杀了你
Means we don't have to kill you ourselves.
没错
You're right.
- 你要去哪? - 我叔叔不杀了我不会善罢甘休的
- Where are you going? - My uncle won't stop until I am dead.
但你不能走 你是来救我们的
But you can't leave. You're meant to save us.
你不知道这是什么吗?
Don't you know what this is?
你的图书馆不错 博士
You have quite a library, doctor.
您要找什么东西吗 阁下?
Is there anything particular you seek, my lord?
我想我已经找到了我想要的…
I think I've already found what I'm looking for...
…从我的一个士兵身上找到了！
...in one of my soldiers!
你知道苏珊女王的号角吗?
What do you know of Queen Susan's horn?
听说那是有魔法的
It was said to be magic.
魔法?
Magic?
纳尼亚人相信它能召唤出 以前的国王和女王
The Narnians believed it could summon their kings and queens of old.
总之 这只是个迷信
At least, such was the superstition.
那凯斯宾知道这个迷信吗?
And what does Caspian know of this superstition?
阁下 你禁止我提及这些古老传说
My lord, you forbade me from mentioning the old tales.
的确如此
So I did.
可以这么说 如果凯斯宾 知道这些高深魔法
I will say this. If Caspian does know of the Deep Magic,
那么阁下确实有理由紧张
my lord would have good reason to be nervous.
首先我们的王子…
First our prince...
…现在他的老师
...now his tutor.
如果米拉兹家的人都不安全
If the members of Miraz's own house are not safe,
- 那我们呢? - 索普匹安大人！
- are any of us? - Lord Sopespian!
说这些话很危险 索普匹安大人
Those are dangerous words, Lord Sopespian.
但现在是危急时期 将军
But these are dangerous times, general.
说话得跟交朋友一样慎重
One should choose his words as carefully as he chooses his friends.
大桥什么时候造好?
How long until the bridge is finished?
- 还在施工中 - 不如人意
- Construction continues on schedule. - That's not good enough.
我要军队现在就渡河
I need my army across that river now.
你可以派些自己的人吗?
May I suggest you contribute some of your own men?
我能调遣的就这么些人
I've only so many at my disposal.
你最好记得
A fact you'd be wise to remember.
去贝鲁那
Go to Beruna.
带够人 我们得在他们之前找到凯斯宾
Take as many troops as you need. We must get to Caspian before they do.
“他们” 阁下?
"They," my lord?
你该学学历史
It's time you learned your history.
他们好安静
They're so still.
他们是树 你还想怎么样?
They're trees. What'd you expect?
他们以前会跳舞
They used to dance.
你们离开不久 台尔玛人就入侵了
Wasn't long after you left that the Telmarines invaded.
活下来的都隐居到森林里了
Those who survived retreated to the woods.
而这些树
And the trees,
隐居地太深 自那以后就没人提及了
they retreated so deep into themselves that they haven't been heard from since.
我不明白 阿斯兰怎么会坐视不理呢?
I don't understand. How could Aslan have let this happen?
阿斯兰?
Aslan?
他和你们一样抛弃我们了
Thought he abandoned us when you lot did.
我们并不想离开的 你知道的
We didn't mean to leave, you know.
现在又有什么分别 不是吗?
Makes no difference now, does it?
带我们去找纳尼亚人…
Get us to the Narnians...
…会不一样的
...and it will.
嗨 你好
Hello, there.
没事 我们是朋友
It's all right. We're friends.
别动 陛下
Don't move, Your Majesty.
离她远点！
Stay away from her!
发射 苏珊！发射！
Shoot, Susan! Shoot!
- 为什么他不停下? - 我想他饿了
- Why wouldn't he stop? - I suspect he was hungry.
谢谢
Thanks.
他很凶悍
He was wild.
我觉得他不会说话
I don't think he could talk at all.
被当成哑巴动物对待太久了
Get treated like a dumb animal long enough,
就变成这样了
that's what you become.
你们会发现纳尼亚 比你们想象中要野蛮地多
You may find Narnia a more savage place than you remember.
我听见了
I can hear you.
我只是觉得我们应该 等待国王和女王的到来
I just think we should wait for the kings and queens.
很好！去啊！看看其他人是否理解！
Fine! Go then! See if the others will be as understanding!
也许我会和你一起去
Or maybe I'll come with you.
我要看看你怎么向牛头人解释
I want to see you explain things to the minotaurs.
牛头人?
Minotaurs?
真的有?
They're real?
脾气很坏
And very bad-tempered.
- 是啊 更不用说体型大 - 庞大
- Yeah, not to mention big. - Huge.
那半人马人呢?他们还存在吗?
What about centaurs? Do they still exist?
嗯 半人马人也许会站在你那边
Well, the centaurs will probably fight on your side.
但不清楚其他人会怎么样
But there's no telling what the others will do.
阿斯兰呢?
What about Aslan?
你怎么会知道我们这么多事?
How do you know so much about us?
- 故事 - 等等
- Stories. - Wait a minute.
你父亲跟你说过纳尼亚的故事?
Your father told you stories about Narnia?
不 是我的老师 他…
No, my professor, he...
听着 我很抱歉
Listen, I'm sorry.
这些不是你们该问的
These are not the kind of questions you should be asking.
- 怎么了? - 人类
- What is it? - Human.
- 他? - 不 他们
- Him? - No. Them.
- 他们在那！ - 快跑！
- There they are! - Run!
冲！
Now!
- 哦 不 - 等等 我去
- Oh, no. - Wait. I'll go.
拿着 走！它比我重要得多
Take it. Go! It's more important than I am.
带他离开这
Get him out of here.
你在哪?
Where are you?
想好了再说遗言 台尔玛人
Choose your last words carefully, Telmarine.
你是只老鼠
You are a mouse.
我还指望有点新意呢
I was hoping for something a little more original.
拿起你的剑
Pick up your sword.
不 谢谢
No, thanks.
拿起来！我不会和手无寸铁的人决斗
Pick it up! I will not fight an unarmed man.
如果我选择不和你兵刃相交
Which is why I might live longer
也许我能活得更久点 尊敬的老鼠先生
if I choose not to cross blades with you, noble mouse.
- 我说了不会和你打 - 我没说过要放过你
I said I would not fight you. I didn't say I'd let you live!
雷佩契普！
Reepicheep!
- 收起你的剑！ - 特鲁佛汉特?
- Stay your blade! - Trufflehunter?
相信你在这种不当时间打扰 一定有很好的理由吧
I trust you have a very good reason for this untimely interruption.
- 他没有 继续 - 是他吹响了号角
- He doesn't. Go ahead. - He's the one who blew the horn.
- 什么? - 让他拿出来看看
- What? - Then let him bring it forward.
我们就是为此聚集在这
This is the reason we have gathered.
我不记得这条路了
I don't remember this way.
那是你们女孩的问题 你们无法记住地图
That's the problem with girls. You can't carry a map in your heads.
那是因为我们记了其它事情
That's because our heads have something in them.
我希望他一开始就能听从D.L.F.
I wish he'd just listen to the D.L.F. In the first place.
- D.L.F.? - 亲爱的小朋友
- D.L. F? - Dear Little Friend.
哦 那根本毫无帮助 不是吗?
Oh, that's not at all patronizing, is it?
我没有迷路
I'm not lost.
不
No.
你走错了
You're just going the wrong way.
你最后一次看到凯斯宾 是在恐怖的森林里
You last saw Caspian at the Shuddering Woods,
去那最快的方法就是渡河
and the quickest way there is to cross at the river Rush.
除非我搞错了 但这里不应该可以渡过去
But unless I'm mistaken, there's no crossing in these parts.
那只能说明 是你搞错了
That explains it, then. You're mistaken.
你看 随着时间 河水侵蚀了泥土 变得更深…
You see, over time, water erodes the earth's soil, carving deeper...
哦 闭嘴
Oh, shut up.
- 有办法下去吗? - 有啊 跳下去
- Is there a way down? - Yeah, falling.
我们没有迷路
Well, we weren't lost.
贝鲁那附近有一个浅滩 游过去怎么样?
There's a ford near Beruna. How do you feel about swimming?
游过去总比走过去好
I'd rather that than walking.
阿斯兰?
Aslan?
是阿斯兰！阿斯兰在那里！
It's Aslan! It's Aslan over there!
你们没看见吗?他就在…
Don't you see? He's right...
…那里
...there.
现在看到了吗?
Do you see him now?
我没发疯
I'm not crazy.
他在那 他要我们跟着他
He was there. He wanted us to follow him.
我想这片森林里有许多狮子
I'm sure there are any number of lions in this wood.
- 就像那只熊 - 我知道那就是阿斯兰
- Just like that bear. - I think I know Aslan when I see him.
听着 我可不想跟着不存在的人
Look, I'm not about to jump off a cliff
跳下悬崖
after someone who doesn't exist.
上次我没相信露西
The last time I didn't believe Lucy
最后以我的愚蠢收场
I ended up looking pretty stupid.
为什么我就没看到他?
Why wouldn't I have seen him?
也许你没在看
Maybe you weren't looking.
对不起 露
I'm sorry, Lu.
杀了他！
Kill him!
- 台尔玛人！ - 骗子！
- Telmarine! - Liar!
凶手！
Murderer!
这个号角只能证明 他们从我们这偷了另一样东西！
All this horn proves is they've stolen yet another thing from us!
- 我什么也没偷 - 没偷?
- I didn't steal anything. - Didn't steal anything?
我们是不是该说下 台尔玛人从我们这夺走的东西?
Shall we list the things the Telmarines have taken?
- 我们的家！ - 我们的土地！
- Our homes! - Our land!
- 我们的自由！ - 我们的生活！
- Our freedom! - Our lives!
你们偷了纳尼亚！
You stole Narnia!
我的人民所犯的一切罪行 你们都要我负责吗?
You would hold me accountable for all the crimes of my people?
负责…
Accountable...
…还有惩罚
...and punishable.
都是因为你们 矮子
That is rich coming from you, dwarf.
难道你忘了 是你的人协助白雪女巫的
Have you forgotten it was your people who fought alongside the White Witch?
我很乐意再做一次 只要能让我们摆脱这些野蛮人
And I'd gladly do it again, if it would rid us of these barbarians.
很幸运你无法带她回来
Then it's lucky that it is not in your power to bring her back.
或者你想让我们叫这男孩去对抗阿斯兰?
Or are you suggesting that we ask this boy to go against Aslan now?
也许你们有些人都忘了 但我们獾却牢牢记着
Some of you may have forgotten, but we badgers remember well,
只有亚当之子成为国王 对纳尼亚才是最正确的
that Narnia was never right except when a Son of Adam was king.
他是台尔玛人！ 为什么要让他当我们的国王?
He's a Telmarine! Why would we want him as our king?
因为我能帮助你们
Because I can help you.
- 这是个诡计！ - 先听他说完！
- It's a trick! - At least hear him out!
在这片森林之外 我是一个王子
Beyond these woods, I'm a prince.
台尔玛王位的合法继承人
The Telmarine throne is rightfully mine!
帮我收回王位 我能为你们带来和平
Help me claim it, and I can bring peace between us.
是真的 时机成熟了
It is true. The time is ripe.
我看着天空
I watch the skies,
正如你记着历史一样 我也在时刻关注着 獾
for it is mine to watch as it is yours to remember, badger.
胜利之王塔瓦 还有和平女神阿兰比尔
Tarva, the lord of victory, and Alambil, the lady of peace,
一同出现在天堂
have come together in the high heavens.
此刻就在这里 亚当之子涌现了…
And now here, a Son of Adam has come forth...
…带给我们久违的自由
...to offer us back our freedom.
这可能吗?你真的相信会有和平吗?
Is this possible? Do you really think there could be peace?
你相信吗?我是说 你真的相信吗?
Do you? I mean, really?
两天前 我不相信世上存在 会说话的动物…
Two days ago, I didn't believe in the existence of talking animals...
…或是矮人…或是半人马人
...or dwarves... or centaurs.
而现在你们就在这 这么多人 这么强大
Yet here you are in strength and numbers
这是我们台尔玛人从未想到过的
that we Telmarines could never have imagined.
无论这只号角是否具有魔力 它把我们聚集到了一起
Whether this horn is magic or not, it brought us together.
齐心协力
And together,
我们还有机会拿回属于我们的东西
we have a chance to take back what is ours.
如果你会带领我们 那么我的儿子们和我…
If you will lead us, then my sons and I...
…愿意为你拔剑
...offer you our swords.
我们愿意无私地为你奉献我们的生命
And we offer you our lives, unreservedly.
米拉兹的军队离我们不远了 阁下
Miraz's army will not be far behind us, sire.
如果我们准备迎击他们 我们得赶快找些士兵和武器
If we are to be ready for them, we need to hurry to find soldiers and weapons.
我肯定他们很快就会来这
I'm sure they will be here soon.
这些！还有这些！
These ones! And these ones!
小心树！
Timber!
- 回来！ - 注意身后！
- Get back! - Watch your back!
小心！
Look out!
- 稳住 稳住！ - 树倒了！
- Steady, steady! - Timber!
也许这不是最好的方法
Perhaps this wasn't the best way to come after all.
你到底在哪看到阿斯兰了?
So where exactly do you think you saw Aslan?
我希望你们都不要装大人说话了
I wish you'd all stop trying to sound like grown-ups.
我不是以为看到他 而是我确实看到了他
I don't think I saw him, I did see him.
我是个大人了
I am a grown-up.
就在…
It was right over...
露西！
Lucy!
…这里
...here.
露西 你没睡着?
Lucy, are you awake?
为什么你们认为我没看到阿斯兰?
Why do you think I didn't see Aslan?
你相信我吗?
You believe me?
看 我们穿过了峡谷
Well, we got across the gorge.
我不知道
I don't know.
也许你不是真的相信
Maybe you didn't really want to.
你一直知道我们会回来 对吗?
You always knew we'd be coming back here, didn't you?
我希望过
I hoped so.
最后我终于能接受在英国的事实了
I finally just got used to the idea of being in England.
但你很高兴在这 对吧?
But you're happy to be here, aren't you?
现在很高兴
While it lasts.
露西
Lucy.
阿斯兰！
Aslan!
我好想你！
I've missed you so much!
- 你长大了 - 每年你都在长大…
- You've grown. - Every year you grow...
…我也是
...so shall I.
你去哪了?为什么你不来帮我们?
Where have you been? Why haven't you come to help us?
事不过二 宝贝
Things never happen the same way twice, dear one.
苏珊！醒醒！
Susan! Wake up!
当然 露 如你所愿
Certainly, Lu. Whatever you like.
醒醒
Wake up.
阿斯兰?
Aslan?
不 住手！
No, stop!
凯斯宾王子?
Prince Caspian?
是的?你是谁?
Yes? And who are you?
彼得！
Peter!
- 彼得至高王 - 我想你在叫我
- High King Peter. - I believe you called.
嗯 是的 但…我觉得你应该老多了
Well, yes, but... I thought you'd be older.
若你希望 我们可以几年后再来…
If you like, we could come back in a few years...
不 不 没关系 你只是…
No. No, that's all right. You're just...
你跟我想的不大一样
You're not exactly what I expected.
你也是
Neither are you.
我们共同的敌人 甚至集结了最古老的仇敌
A common enemy unites even the oldest of foes.
我们焦急地等待您的归来 陛下
We have anxiously awaited your return, my liege.
我们的心和剑随时供您差遣
Our hearts and swords are at your service.
哦 天哪 他太可爱了
Oh, my gosh, he is so cute.
- 谁在说? - 抱歉
- Who said that? - Sorry.
陛下 致上我最崇高的敬意
Your Majesty, with the greatest respect,
我相信“勇气” “礼貌”或“风度”
I do believe "courageous," "courteous," or "chivalrous"
更适合一个纳尼亚勇士
might more befit a knight of Narnia.
至少我们知道你们中的一些还能拿动剑
Well, at least we know some of you can handle a blade.
是的 确实如此 我最近找到了他们的用武之地
Yes, indeed. And I have recently put it to good use,
为您的军队守卫武器 陛下
securing weapons for your army, sire.
很好 我们需要尽可能多的剑
Good. Because we're going to need every sword we can get.
那么 也许你想拿回你的剑
Well, then, you will probably be wanting yours back.
他们拿走了多少?
How much did they take?
足够配备两个团的武器和盔甲
Enough weapons and armor for two regiments.
但是…还不止如此
But... there's more.
“害怕森林是对的”
"You were right to fear the woods."
- “X”? - 凯斯宾 第十任
- "X"? - Caspian. The tenth.
很抱歉 阁下 是我的错
I apologize, my lord. The blame is mine.
我知道
I know.
告诉我 将军…
Tell me, general...
…你们失去了多少人?
...how many men did you lose?
- 一个也没有 阁下 - 一个也没?
- None, my lord. - None?
他们深夜潜入 我们根本就没看到他们
They came like ghosts, in the dead of night. We never saw them.
那你如何解释你的伤?
Then how do you explain your injuries?
我是问…
I asked...
…在纳尼亚人的这场血腥袭击中
...how many men were killed
有多少人被杀?
during this bloody Narnian attack?
你能活下来真是幸运
Of which you were a fortunate survivor.
将军…
General...
…多少人?
...how many?
3个
Three.
很抱歉 索普匹安大人
I apologize, Lord Sopespian.
凯斯宾不是这场野蛮暴乱的受害者
Caspian is not a victim of this savage uprising.
他是煽动者
He is the instigator.
看起来纳尼亚很需要一个新的国王
It seems Narnia is in need of a new king.
你们有军队真是太好了
Well, it's good you have troops,
但我们还需要些防御工事 一些准备瞄准的地方
but we need some fortifications. Somewhere to train.
那么?他们怎么样?
So? What are they like?
- 不满 抱怨 固执 - 就如早晨的倔驴
Malcontents, complainers, stubborn as mules in the morning.
那么你喜欢他们咯
So you like them, then.
够了
Well enough.
也许和以前不一样了 但这还能防御
It may not be what you are used to, but it is defensible.
彼得 也许你想看看这个
Peter. You may want to see this.
是我们
It's us.
这是什么地方?
What is this place?
你们不知道?
You don't know?
他一定知道自己在干嘛
He must know what he's doing.
现在得靠我们自己
I think it's up to us now.
只是时间问题
It's only a matter of time.
米拉兹的军队和战争机器已经在路上了
Miraz's men and war machines are on their way.
也就是说这些人不可能在守卫城堡
That means those same men aren't protecting his castle.
您希望我们怎么做 陛下?
What do you propose we do, Your Majesty?
- 我们得做好准备 - 为了开始准备…
- We need to get ready for it. - To start planning for...
我们唯一的希望就是先他们出手
Our only hope is to strike them before they strike us.
疯了 从没有人攻陷过那城堡
Crazy. No one has taken that castle.
- 总有第一次 - 我们可以出其不意
- There's always a first time. - We'll have the element of surprise.
- 但是在这我们有优势！ - 如果我们继续挖
- But we have the advantage here! - If we dig in,
也许我们可以长时间拖延他们
we could probably hold them off indefinitely.
我还是觉得地下更安全
I, for one, feel safer underground.
看 我很欣赏你在这所做的
Look. I appreciate what you've done here,
但这不是一个堡垒 而是坟墓
but this isn't a fortress. It's a tomb.
是啊 如果台尔玛人聪明的话
Yes. And if they're smart,
他们就会跟我们打持久战 把我们饿死
the Telmarines will just wait and starve us out.
- 我们可以收集坚果！ - 是啊！然后扔向台尔玛人
- We could collect nuts! - Yes! And throw them at the Telmarines.
闭嘴！
Shut up!
我想你应该知道我的立场 阁下
I think you know where I stand, sire.
如果我把你的军队带进去 你能解决守卫吗?
If I get your troops in, can you handle the guards?
誓死完成 陛下
Or die trying, my liege.
- 这正是我所担心的 - 什么?
- That's what I'm worried about. - Sorry?
你们表现得就如只有两条路可走
You're all acting like there's only two options.
要么死在这 要么死在那
Dying here, or dying there.
- 我不确定你是不是在听 - 不 你没在听
- I'm not sure you've been listening. - No, you're not listening.
难道你们忘了是谁 最后打败了白雪女巫的 彼得?
Or have you forgotten who really defeated the White Witch, Peter?
我觉得我们等阿斯兰够久了
I think we've waited for Aslan long enough.
老师?
Professor?
- 我得找到他 - 你没时间了
- I have to find him. - You don't have time.
- 你必须去把门打开 - 没有他 你不会在这
- You need to get the gate open. - You wouldn't be here without him.
我也不会
And neither would I.
我们俩能搞定米拉兹
You and I can deal with Miraz.
我仍能按时到大门那
And I can still get to the gate in time.
是的 我是只老鼠
Yes, I'm a mouse.
你知道 我们都希望是个个子高点的人
We were expecting someone, you know, taller.
- 是你在说话啊 - 那是在挖苦人吗?
- You're one to talk. - Is that supposed to be irony?
还有五分钟?
Five more minutes?
你在这干嘛?
What are you doing here?
我帮你逃跑 不是为了让你闯进来的
I didn't help you escape just so you could break back in.
在米拉兹发现你之前
You have to get out
你快点离开这
before Miraz learns you're here.
他很快就会发现
He's going to learn soon enough.
我们会把他扔进你的牢房
We are giving him your cell.
不要像你父亲一样低估米拉兹
Don't underestimate Miraz as your father did.
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
谢天谢地你没事
Thank goodness you're safe.
起来
Get up.
- 凯斯宾? - 别动
- Caspian? - Stay where you are.
- 你在干什么? - 很明显啊 亲爱的
- What are you doing? - I should think it's obvious, dear.
你知道 有些家庭会认为这是种不当行为
You know, some families might consider this inappropriate behavior.
看起来这不能阻止你
That doesn't seem to have stopped you!
但你跟我不像 不是吗?
But you are not like me, are you?
真悲哀 第一次你那么有骨气…
It's sad. The first time you've shown any backbone...
…却还是可惜了
...and it's such a waste.
把剑放下 凯斯宾
Put the sword down, Caspian.
- 我不想这样做 - 我们也不想你这么做
- I don't want to do this. - We don't want you to either.
这以前是个私人房间
This used to be a private room.
你在干什么?你应该在警卫室
What are you doing? You're supposed to be in the gatehouse!
不！
No!
就今晚 我要知道真相
Tonight for once, I want the truth.
是你杀了我父亲?
Did you kill my father?
现在进入正题
Now we get to it.
你说你哥哥死于睡梦中
You said your brother died in his sleep.
那或许是真的
That was more or less true.
凯斯宾 这么做没什么用
Caspian, this won't make things any better.
我们台尔玛人如果不抢 就什么也不会有
We Telmarines would have nothing had we not taken it.
你父亲明白这点 其他人也一样
Your father knew that as well as anyone.
你怎么能这么做?
How could you?
跟你射箭一样的原因
For the same reason you will pull that trigger.
- 为了我们的儿子 - 住手！
- For our son. - Stop!
- 呆那别动 - 你得做个选择 亲爱的
- Stay right there. - You need to make a choice, dear.
想让我们的孩子成为国王吗?
Do you want our child to be king?
或者你想让他跟凯斯宾一样?
Or do you want him to be like Caspian here?
- 没有父亲！ - 不！
- Fatherless! - No!
凯斯宾！
Caspian!
那是什么意思?
What's that supposed to mean?
- 我们受到攻击了！ - 敲警钟！
- We're under attack! - Sound the alarm!
伙计们！拿起你们的弓！
Men! Grab your bows!
- 彼得！ - 我们的军队就在外面！快！
- Peter! - Our troops are just outside! Come on!
快 埃德！动手！
Now, Ed! Now!
- 给军队发信号 - 我顾不过来 彼得！
- Signal the troops! - I'm a bit busy, Pete!
彼得！太迟了！ 我们必须取消行动
Peter! It's too late. We have to call it off while we can.
不 还能做！
No, I can still do this!
帮帮我！
Help me!
你这么做到底是为了谁 彼得?
Exactly who are you doing this for, Peter?
快！
Come on!
冲啊！
Charge!
我们受到攻击了！
We're under attack!
进攻！进攻！
Attack! Attack!
为了纳尼亚！
For Narnia!
弓箭手！
Archers!
选中目标！
Pick a target!
瞄准！
Take aim!
埃德！
Ed!
把门关上
Get that gate closed.
回去！
Fall back!
我们必须撤退！立刻！
We need to retreat! Now!
去！把她带走！
Go! Get her out of here!
回到大门那！快！
Back to the gate! Go!
- 凯斯宾！ - 我会找到他！
- Caspian! - I'll find him!
走！出去！快走！出去！撤退！
Go! Get out! Go! Get out! Retreat!
跟着我！
Follow me!
下命令
Give the order.
我的人还在那
My men are still down there.
回去！离开这！撤退！
Draw back! Get out! Retreat!
发射！
Now!
Fire!
快跑！保住性命！
Run for your life! Save yourself!
彼得！吊桥！
Peter! The bridge!
别管我们！走吧 兄弟们！
Leave us! Go, brothers!
以阿斯兰之名！
In the name of Aslan!
发生了什么事?
What happened?
问他
Ask him.
- 彼得 - 我?
- Peter. - Me?
你可以取消计划的 还有时间
You could've called it off. There was still time.
不 没时间了 都是因为你
No, there wasn't, thanks to you.
如果按原计划进行 那些士兵可以存活下来
If you kept to the plan, those soldiers might be alive.
如果你听我的话留在这里 他们肯定能活！
If you'd stayed here like I suggested, they definitely would be!
- 是你叫我们的 记得吗? - 那是我第一个错误
- You called us, remember? - My first mistake.
不 你的第一个错误是 自以为能领导这些人
No. Your first mistake was thinking you could lead these people.
丢下纳尼亚的人不是我
I am not the one who abandoned Narnia.
你入侵了纳尼亚 比起米拉兹 你更没资格统治它
You invaded Narnia. You have no more right to lead it than Miraz does.
你 他 还有你父亲…
You, him, your father...
没有你们这种人纳尼亚会更好
Narnia's better off without the lot of you.
住手！
Stop it!
你们都围着干什么?
What are you all standing around for?
台尔玛人很快就会到这里
Telmarines will be here soon enough.
谢谢你…我亲爱的小朋友
Thank you... my dear little friend.
- 小伙子们 干得好 - 伙计 太慢了！动作快一点
- Well done, lads. - Move it faster, mate. Too slow!
贝鲁那的军队集结完毕
Beruna pledges its troops.
伽尔玛的军队集结完毕
Galma pledges its troops.
塔什班的军队集结完毕
Tashbaan pledges its troops.
艾汀斯莫的军队集结完毕
Ettinsmoor pledges its troops.
国王万岁！ 国王万岁！
Long live the king! Long live the king!
拥有那魔法号角 你现在很开心吧 小子?
Are you so glad of that magic horn now, boy?
你的国王和女王令我们失望
Your kings and queens have failed us.
你的军队已死伤过半 剩下的也时日无多
Your army's half dead. And those that aren't will be soon enough.
你想要什么?恭贺?
What do you want? Congratulations?
你想要你叔叔的鲜血 我们也是
You want your uncle's blood. So do we.
你要他的王位吗?我们可以帮你
You want his throne? We can get it for you.
你尝试了一种古老的力量 但失败了
You tried one ancient power. It failed.
但仍然有更强大的力量
But there is a power greater still.
一种甚至能牵制住阿斯兰近百年的力量
One that kept even Aslan at bay for near a hundred years.
谁在那里?
Who's there?
我饿了
I am hunger.
我渴了
I am thirst.
我可以禁食一百年…
I can fast a hundred years...
…而不死亡
...and not die.
我可以躺在冰上一百年…
I can lie a hundred nights on the ice...
…而不冻僵
...and not freeze.
我可以喝光一条河的血而不溃决
I can drink a river of blood and not burst.
让我看看 …你的敌人！
Show me... your enemies!
你憎恨什么 我们也一样
What you hate, so will we.
没人比我们更心存仇恨
No one hates better than us.
你可以…保证米拉兹会死吗?
And you can... guarantee Miraz's death?
还不止呢
And more.
画圈吧
Let the circle be drawn.
等等
Wait.
这不是我想要的
This isn't what I wanted.
只要亚当的一滴血 就可以解封我
One drop of Adam's blood and you free me.
然后我会臣服于你 我的国王
Then I am yours, my king.
不！
No!
停下！
Stop!
过来吧！过来
Come on! Come.
离他远点！
Get away from him!
彼得 亲爱的
Peter, dear.
我很想念你
I've missed you.
来吧
Come.
只要一滴
Just one drop.
你知道你独自一人完成不了
You know you can't do this alone.
我知道 你搞定它了
I know. You had it sorted.
为什么你从不告诉我父亲的事?
Why did you never tell me about my father?
我母亲是北部山区的一个黑矮人
My mother was a Black Dwarf from the Northern Mountains.
这些年来我冒着生命危险
I risked my life all these years
是为了有朝一日…
so that one day...
…你能成为有史以来最伟大的国王
...you might be a better king than those before you.
但我让你失望了
Then I have failed you.
告诉过你的事 还有没有告诉过你的
Everything I told you, everything I didn't,
都只是因为我相信你
it was only because I believe in you.
你有机会成为史上 最崇高 最不一样的国王
You have a chance to become the most noble contradiction in history.
成为拯救纳尼亚的那个台尔玛人
The Telmarine who saved Narnia.
你知道吗 你很幸运
You're lucky, you know.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
看到了他
To have seen him.
我希望他能给我点证明
I wish he'd just given me some sort of proof.
也许我们才应该给他证明
Maybe we're the ones who need to prove ourselves to him.
彼得 你快过来看看
Pete. You'd better come quickly.
蛋糕与铜鼓 那就是你下一步大计?
Cakes and kettledrums. That's your next big plan?
把一个小女孩送到森林最黑暗的角落? 让她独自一人！
Sending a little girl into the darkest parts of the forest? Alone!
- 这是我们唯一的机会 - 我们不会丢下她
- It's our only chance. - And she won't be alone.
死的人还不够多吗?
Haven't enough of us died already?
尼卡布瑞克也是我的朋友 但他失去希望了
Nikabrik was my friend too. But he lost hope.
露西女王还心存希望 我也一样
Queen Lucy hasn't. And neither have I.
为了阿斯兰
For Aslan.
为了阿斯兰！
For Aslan!
- 那我跟你们一起去 - 不 这里需要你
- Then I'm going with you. - No. We need you here.
在露西和苏珊回来前 我们得拖住他们
We have to hold them off until Lucy and Susan get back.
如果我可以…
If I may...
米拉兹或许是一个暴君 一个凶手…
Miraz may be a tyrant and a murderer...
…但作为一国之君 他遵从传统
...but as king, he is subject to the traditions...
…和人民的期望
...and expectations of his people.
我有个计划 或许能为我们争取点时间
There is one in particular that may buy us some time.
他们可能想投降
Perhaps they intend to surrender.
不
No.
他们太骄矜了
They are much too noble for that.
“通过选拔与征服 蒙阿斯兰恩赐 我 彼得
"I, Peter, by the gift of Aslan, by election and by conquest,
纳尼亚至高王 卡尔帕斯维尔统治者 孤岛君主
High King of Narnia, Lord of Cair Paravel and emperor of the Lone Islands,
为了避免令人憎恶的流血事件
in order to prevent the abominable effusion of blood,
在此挑战篡夺者米拉兹 在战场上一对一
do hereby challenge the usurper Miraz to single combat upon the field of battle.
至死方休 输者将完全臣服”
The fight shall be to the death. The reward shall be total surrender."
- 告诉我 埃德蒙王子… - 国王
- Tell me, Prince Edmund... - King.
- 再说一遍? - 应该是埃德蒙国王
- Pardon me? - It's King Edmund, actually.
只是“国王”而已 彼得才是至高王
Just "King," though. Peter's the high king.
我知道这会令人混淆
I know, it's confusing.
为什么我们要冒险接受你的提议?
Why would we risk such a proposal
我们的军队黄昏前就可以铲平你们
when our armies could wipe you out by nightfall?
你们不早就低估了我们的数量了吗?
Haven't you already underestimated our numbers?
我是说 一星期前 纳尼亚人就灭绝了
I mean, only a week ago Narnians were extinct.
你们会步他们的后尘
And so you will be again.
那你们就没什么好害怕的了
Well, then you should have little to fear.
这不是勇不勇敢的问题
This is not a question of bravery.
那你是勇敢地拒绝跟一个 只有你一半年纪的军人决斗?
So you're bravely refusing to fight a swordsman half your age?
我没说我拒绝
I didn't say I refused.
陛下 无论你决定怎样
You shall have our support, Your Majesty.
我们都支持你
Whatever your decision.
阁下 我们的军事优势 足以给我们理由去避免
Sire, our military advantage alone provides the perfect excuse to avoid
- 有可能造成… - 我不会逃避什么！
- what might otherwise be... - I'm not avoiding anything!
我只是指出而已
I was merely pointing out
陛下您有权拒绝
that my lord is well within his rights to refuse.
陛下从来不会拒绝
His Majesty would never refuse.
他很珍惜这样一个向人民展示
He relishes the chance to show the people
新国王勇气的机会
the courage of their new king.
你
You.
你最好指望你哥哥的剑 比他的笔尖更锋利
You should hope your brother's sword is sharper than his pen.
德斯瑞尔一直是我的好坐骑 你们有了个好帮手了
Destrier has always served me well. You are in good hands.
是好“帮蹄”吧
Or hooves.
- 祝你好运 - 谢谢
- Good luck. - Thanks.
看
Look.
或者你该拿回这个了
Maybe it is time you had this back.
为什么你不留着它 或许你还要召唤我的
Why don't you hold on to it. You might need to call me again.
- 或许你还要召唤我的? - 哦 闭嘴
- You might need to call me again? - Oh, shut up.
如果情况不太妙的话…
If it should appear to be going poorly...
明白 陛下
Understood, Your Majesty.
希望我胜出的时候 你们不会太失望
I hope you won't be too disappointed when I survive.
现在投降还来得及
There is still time to surrender.
放松
Well, feel free.
为了王位还要死多少人?
How many more must die for the throne?
就一个
Just one.
- 跑！ - 他们看到我们了！
- Ride! - They've seen us!
- 抓住缰绳 - 你要干什么?
- Take the reins. - What are you doing?
抱歉 露西 看来最后你还是得一个人去
I'm sorry, Lucy. But it looks as if you'll be going alone after all.
你确定不需要那个号角了?
Are you sure you don't need that horn?
殿下需要中场休息吗?
Does His Highness need a respite?
五分钟?
Five minutes?
三分钟！
Three!
露西?
Lucy?
她过去了…得到了一点帮助
She got through... with a little help.
- 谢谢 - 你在忙啊
- Thanks. - Well, you were busy.
我猜你不会让他们再次靠近！
I assume you won't let things get that close again!
你最好到上面去 以防万一
You better get up there. Just in case.
我不指望台尔玛人会守信
I don't expect the Telmarines will keep their word.
- 对不起 - 没事
- Sorry. - It's all right.
小心
Be careful.
保持微笑
Keep smiling.
你觉得他怎么样?
How does he look to you?
年轻
Young.
但以年纪来看…陛下做得很好了
But His Majesty's doing extremely well... for his age.
我想是脱臼了
I think it's dislocated.
如果你死在这里 家那边会怎样?
What do you think happens back home if you die here?
你一直在帮我 可我却从未真正…
You know you've always been there, and I never really...
稍后再说
Save it for later.
休息！
Respite!
休息
Respite.
彼得 现在不是秀骑士精神的时候
Now's not the time for chivalry, Peter!
不要手软！
Show no mercy!
小心！
Look out!
怎么了 小子?
What's the matter, boy?
杀人都不敢吗?
Too cowardly to take a life?
不该由我来杀
It's not mine to take.
也许我错了
Perhaps I was wrong.
或者你确实有资格成为台尔玛国王
Maybe you do have the makings of a Telmarine king after all.
不会像你一样
Not one like you.
饶你一命
Keep your life.
但我会把纳尼亚人的王国归还给他们
But I am giving the Narnians back their kingdom.
我的国王
My king.
完事后再找你算账
I'll deal with you when this is over.
结束了
It is over.
背信弃义！他们射死了陛下！
Treachery! They shot him!
他们杀害了我们的国王！
They murdered our king!
全体准备！
Be ready!
彼得！
Peter!
走！
Go!
举起武器 台尔玛！
To arms, Telmar!
举起武器！
To arms!
发射！
Loose!
骑兵准备！
Cavalry!
进攻！
Attack!
弓箭手准备！
Archers to the ready!
纳尼亚人准备！
Narnians!
进攻！
Charge!
一 二…
One, two...
三 四…
Three, four...
五 六…
Five, six...
举弓！
Take your aim!
瞄准他们！
Stay with them!
八 九…
Eight, nine...
准备！
Get ready!
冲啊！
Now!
停下！后退！后退！
Stop! Back! Back!
稳住！稳住！
Hold it now! Hold it!
发射！
Now!
冲啊！
Charge!
是只老鼠
You're a mouse.
你们这些人真没想象力
You people have no imagination.
发射 发射！
Loose! Loose!
露西?
Lucy?
撤回堡垒！
Back to the How!
别让他们逃了！
Cut off their escape!
发射！
Loose!
准备好！
Brace yourselves!
撤回堡垒！
Back to the How!
全部砸烂它
Crush them all.
阿斯兰！
Aslan!
我知道是你 一直都知道
I knew it was you. The whole time, I knew it.
但其他人不相信我
But the others didn't believe me.
为什么他们不相信你 你就不来找我呢?
And why would that stop you from coming to me?
对不起 我害怕自己一个人来
I'm sorry. I was too scared to come alone.
你为什么不现身?
Why wouldn't you show yourself?
为什么你不像上次那样 咆哮而来拯救我们呢?
Why couldn't you come roaring in and save us like last time?
亲爱的 事不过二
Things never happen the same way twice, dear one.
如果我早点来 死了的人… 我就能阻止吗?
If I'd have come earlier, would everyone who died... could I have stopped that?
露西 我们永远无法知道如果的事
We can never know what would have happened, Lucy.
但将要发生什么却完全是另一码事
But what will happen is another matter entirely.
- 你意思是你会出手帮助? - 当然
- You mean you'll help? - Of course.
- 你也会的 - 哦 我希望当时我能勇敢些
- As will you. - Oh, I wish I was braver.
你更勇敢的话就成了头母狮了
If you were any braver, you'd be a lioness.
我想你的朋友们睡得够久了 不是吗?
Now, I think your friends have slept long enough, don't you?
来吧！
Come on!
露西
Lucy.
为了阿斯兰！
For Aslan!
如果我们把他们引到河边 就能打败他们
We can defeat them if we draw them to the river.
我们必须重整队伍 去贝鲁那！
We must regroup. To Beruna!
去桥那！
To the bridge!
冲啊！
Charge!
发生什么事了?
What is happening?
- 大浪！ - 撤退！
- The river! - Retreat!
退后！退后！
Back! Back!
不要
Come on.
在河岸集合！
Assemble on that bank!
不会伤害你们！
You will not be harmed!
交出武器！
Surrender your weapons!
卸下盔甲！
Take off the armor!
起来 纳尼亚的国王和女王
Rise, kings and queens of Narnia.
都起来
All of you.
我想我还没准备好
I do not think I am ready.
正因为这个原因 我认为你已经准备好了
It's for that very reason I know you are.
谢谢你 陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢谢
Thank you.
阿斯兰万岁！ 真是荣幸 能够…
Hail, Aslan! It is a great honor to be in...
形象全毁了
I'm completely out of countenance.
请原谅我如此不体面地出现
I must crave your indulgence for appearing in this unseemly fashion.
再来一滴如何?
Perhaps a drop more?
- 我觉得那没用 - 你可以试一下
- I don't think it does that. - You could have a go.
它让你活了 小东西
It becomes you well, small one.
我完全同意 伟大的国王
All the same, great king,
恐怕我要引退了 因为尾巴对老鼠来说是尊严和荣耀
I regret that I must withdraw, for a tail is the honor and glory of a mouse.
朋友 或许你把尊严看得太重了
Perhaps you think too much of your honor, friend.
不只是尊严问题 它对平衡也很重要
Well, it's not just the honor. It's also great for balance.
还有攀爬 抓东西
And climbing. And grabbing things.
请您原谅 陛下 我们无法忍受
May it please Your High Majesty, we will not bear the shame
这种有毁领袖尊严的耻辱
of wearing an honor denied to our chief.
并不是为了你的尊严
Not for the sake of your dignity,
而是为了你对人民的爱
but for the love of your people.
看！谢谢 陛下 我会永远珍惜它的
Look! Thank you, my liege. I will treasure it always.
从今天开始 它将时刻提醒我这次巨大的耻辱
From this day forward it will serve as a great reminder of my huge humility.
现在 你们经常跟我提起的 那个小朋友呢?
Now, where is this dear little friend you've told me so much about?
现在你看到他了吗?
Do you see him now?
因为你们是溜进来的…
Because you have snuck in...
对不起 但他们在那个世界的 未来是美好的
I'm sorry, but their future in that world shall be good.
陛下?
Your Majesty?
我们准备好了 大家都集合了
We are ready. Everyone has assembled.
纳尼亚属于纳尼亚人 也属于人类
Narnia belongs to the Narnians, just as it does to man.
欢迎任何想留下和平共处的台尔玛人
Any Telmarines who want to stay and live in peace are welcome to.
但如果你们想的话
But for any of you who wish,
阿斯兰会把你们送回我们祖先的家园
Aslan will return you to the home of our forefathers.
我们离开台尔玛已经有几代了
It's been generations since we left Telmar.
我们所说的不是台尔玛
We're not referring to Telmar.
你们的祖先曾是搁浅在一座岛上的
Your ancestors were seafaring brigands.
海贼和海盗
Pirates run aground on an island.
他们在那发现了一个山洞 罕见的裂口把他们从自己的世界带到了这
There they found a cave, a rare chasm that brought them here from their world.
我们的国王和女王也来自同一个世界
The same world as our kings and queens.
我可以把你们送回那座岛
It is to that island I can return you.
对于任何想重新开始的人来说 那是个好地方
It is a good place for any who wish to make a new start.
我要去
I will go.
我接受这个建议
I will accept the offer.
我们也去
So will we.
因为你们最先报名 你们在那个世界将会有个幸福的未来
Because you have spoken first, your future in that world shall be good.
- 他们去了哪里? - 被杀了
- Where did they go? - They killed them.
我们怎么知道他不是让我们去送死呢?
How do we know he is not leading us to our death?
陛下 如果我的示范能起作用的话
Sire. If my example can be of any service,
我愿意立刻带十一只老鼠进去
I will take 11 mice through with no delay.
- 我们也去 - 我们?
- We'll go. - We will?
来吧 是时候了
Come on. Our time's up.
毕竟…
After all...
…这里不需要我们了
...we're not really needed here anymore.
我帮你保管着 直到你回来
I will look after it until you return.
我恐怕就到此为止了
I'm afraid that's just it.
我们不会回来了
We're not coming back.
我们不会?
We're not?
你们两个会
You two are.
至少 我认为他是指你们两个
At least, I think he means you two.
为什么?
But why?
- 他们做错了什么? - 亲爱的 正好相反
- Did they do something wrong? - Quite the opposite, dear one.
但万物都有它的期限
But all things have their time.
你的哥哥和姐姐已经在这个世界 学到了他们要学的东西
Your brother and sister have learned what they can from this world.
现在是时候让他们回到自己的世界
Now it's time for them to live in their own.
事情会好起来的 露
It's all right, Lu.
一切并不如我想的那样…
It's not how I thought it would be...
…但这没关系
...but it's all right.
总有一天你也会明白 来吧
One day you'll see, too. Come on.
很高兴我回来了
I'm glad I came back.
真希望我们能有更多时间在一起
I wish we had more time together.
总之那是不可能的
It would never have worked, anyway.
为什么不?
Why not?
我比你老了一千三百岁
I am 1,300 years older than you.
我肯定 当我老了我会明白的
I'm sure when I'm older I'll understand.
我比你老 但我才不想明白呢
I'm older and don't think I want to understand.
菲利斯 你不上车吗?
Aren't you coming, Phyllis?
你觉得我们没有其他办法回去了吗?
You don't think there's any way we can get back?
我把我的新手电筒留在纳尼亚了
I've left my new torch in Narnia.